<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-05-31T18:01:37-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Meromorphy</title><subtitle>Me and my random thoughts.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Meromorphy - A Quotient of Understanding</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/05/25/meromrophy-quotient-of-understanding.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Meromorphy - A Quotient of Understanding" /><published>2025-05-25T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-05-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/05/25/meromrophy-quotient-of-understanding</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/05/25/meromrophy-quotient-of-understanding.html"><![CDATA[<blockquote style="border-left: 4px solidrgb(95, 132, 205); padding-left: 1em; color: solidrgb(95, 132, 205); margin: 1.5em 0; font-style: italic;">
  “The mind may be continuous, but meaning often arises near the points where it isn’t.”
</blockquote>

<p>We often think of mystery as a void — a sudden absence of understanding. A rupture in an otherwise smooth field. But mathematics offers us a subtler picture: sometimes what looks like mystery is actually structure failing just slightly — in a way we can name, analyze, and even integrate.</p>

<p><em>Understanding as a Ratio:</em> A meromorphic function, for instance, is a ratio of two holomorphic functions. On its own, it looks mostly well-behaved — smooth, differentiable, almost serene. But at isolated points, the denominator vanishes. The function spikes, becomes undefined. We call these poles. And yet, these aren’t wild breakdowns. They’re precise, knowable failures. We know why the spike occurs, where it happens, how it behaves around the edge. Even the disruption has a shape. Moreover, even at those poles, something remains — residues, a kind of fingerprint left by the singularities at the poles. Astonishingly, when we integrate such functions — when we try to understand them as a whole — we do it not by ignoring the singularities, but by summing the residues they leave behind. Their contributions are not errors to be discarded. They are essential to the total structure.</p>

<p>That, to me, feels more like life than most metaphors we’re given.</p>

<p><em>The Shape of Breakdowns:</em> We are, each of us, quotient structures — built from rational parts, histories, thoughts, memories, assumptions, values — and yet prone to discontinuity at very specific places. Not everywhere. Just here and there. A trauma. A death. A loss of meaning. A crisis of belief. These don’t undo the whole function. But they mark its poles. And like the mathematical function, we don’t fall apart entirely at those points — we behave strangely, but still legibly. There’s something to be studied, something to be felt, even in our jaggedness. We remain coherent in every direction except the one we can’t quite approach.</p>

<p><em>Grief and the Residue of Loss:</em> Take grief, for instance. When someone you love is alive, you know them. You understand their humor, their flaws, the weight of their silence, the rhythm of their breath in a room. Then they’re gone — and suddenly, the denominator vanishes. You are left with a numerator full of memory, habit, and love, divided by a complete and unresolvable absence. The singularity isn’t just the loss; it’s the impossibility of fitting that absence into the rest of your life. But you don’t stop living. You loop around it. You adapt your motion. You contour your choices around its presence. And in doing so, something remains: the residue of that loss — how it changes your posture in the world, how it sharpens your sense of time, how it softens you toward others’ suffering. The residue doesn’t vanish. It helps complete your arc.</p>

<p><em>Hidden Structure of Mental Health:</em> Or take mental health — your own, or someone else’s. A person may be warm, articulate, engaged — and then suddenly overwhelmed, withdrawn, reactive. From the outside, it looks like a break in behavior. A pole. Something that doesn’t compute. But if you could see the hidden denominator — the accumulation of past experience, inner logic, and silent battles — you’d realize it’s not chaos. It’s structure you don’t yet see. And even when we can’t resolve it, we can often understand the residue it leaves — patterns of caution, bursts of empathy, the quiet strength of someone who’s survived. You might not be able to explain or “fix” the pole, but you can learn to integrate around it. To carry its contribution into your relationship with them. To see it not as a failure, but as a formation.</p>

<p><em>What Lingers After the Pole:</em> This, to me, is the real gift of meromorphy — not just that singularities exist, but that they matter. That our most profound ruptures leave something behind that can be folded into meaning. That we are integrable, not because we are whole, but because we are shaped by where we are not. The residue of grief. The residue of trauma. The residue of joy so intense it frightened you. These are not footnotes to your life. They’re part of the equation.</p>

<p>And maybe that’s a kind of mercy. That our singularities don’t define our dysfunction, but our contribution. That even our breaks leave behind something measurable, meaningful — something that helps us complete the arc.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“The mind may be continuous, but meaning often arises near the points where it isn’t.”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Meromorphy - A Map of the Known and the Broken</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/04/24/meromorphy-a-map-of-the-known-and-the-broken.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Meromorphy - A Map of the Known and the Broken" /><published>2025-04-24T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-04-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/04/24/meromorphy-a-map-of-the-known-and-the-broken</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/04/24/meromorphy-a-map-of-the-known-and-the-broken.html"><![CDATA[<p>In mathematics, a meromorphic function is something that behaves—well, almost perfectly. It’s smooth, logical, and beautifully structured until it’s not. At certain isolated points, called poles, the function just loses its cool and shoots off to infinity. These aren’t flaws exactly. They’re part of the design. A meromorphic function is allowed to break, but only in very specific, well-documented ways.</p>

<p>I’ve always found that idea oddly comforting. It feels like an honest description not just of functions, but of people. Of life. Of the universe.</p>

<p>We, too, are mostly well-behaved—predictable, learnable, explainable. We follow patterns. We build frameworks. We read articles titled “10 Principles of Something” because we believe, quite reasonably, that things can be understood.</p>

<p>And yet, each of us has our own poles.
Personal ones. Quiet ones. Some tender, some terrifying.
Places where logic fails and emotion takes over, or where memory refuses to resolve, or where a question just keeps echoing without answer.</p>

<p>The world has its poles too. Science has done a remarkable job explaining what’s going on—from the subatomic to the cosmic. But even now, there are things that remain stubbornly outside the equation. Consciousness. Time. Death. The part of your brain that lights up when you hear a certain piece of music and, for a moment, you feel both completely alive and totally unknowable.</p>

<p>So that’s what Meromorphy is. It’s a place to write from within the known, but always facing the edge of the unknown. It’s not a blog about math (though it might flirt with it now and then). It’s a space for science, life, innovation, and being human—being mostly coherent, but not entirely.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In mathematics, a meromorphic function is something that behaves—well, almost perfectly. It’s smooth, logical, and beautifully structured until it’s not. At certain isolated points, called poles, the function just loses its cool and shoots off to infinity. These aren’t flaws exactly. They’re part of the design. A meromorphic function is allowed to break, but only in very specific, well-documented ways.]]></summary></entry></feed>